Dr. Karan Mittal: That we know of, or…
Dr. Karan Mittal: wind and ether, time and direction, that is dhik and kala, are also considered as two important elements in our Indian philosophy, Indian shastras. And from these two elements, we derive the shastras of Vastu, that is dhik, direction, and kala, that is time, that is.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Jyotisha Shastra. We also saw that how these Shastras are different kind of windows to the same room of our life. We can see a person from the perspective of Vastu, we can see a person from the perspective of astrology, we can see a person from the perspective of
Dr. Karan Mittal: Psychology, different windows to the same room of life, and how we can use these different perspectives to kind of modify our life for our best performance, or for our best.
Dr. Karan Mittal: benevolent, you know, performance and different decisions of our life. So that's another aspect that we saw. We also saw that,
Dr. Karan Mittal: how astrology is more of a Shastra of probabilities, rather than final verdicts. So, Rishi's also refrained from it, but they gave us many probabilities of how different, different combinations and permutations lead to different probabilities in a person's life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: We saw this in Dhanta of Yat Pindet and Gurmani, that is
Dr. Karan Mittal: What reflects in the universe also reflects in our body and vice versa, so our placement of the 9 planets in our body is also there, different different organs, different different chakras are controlled and governed by different planets. Those same planets are placed in our Vastu, that is in our house, and both interact with each other and on a higher plane or higher reality.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the same planets exist in a solar system. So, kind of aligning these three leads to the betterment of human pursuits. That is the fourth Ushrata that we spoke about. We discussed about…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of the Lagna Rashi and the Chandra Rashi, how the Lagna Rashi is
Dr. Karan Mittal: How the world looks at you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: What's your… what's your understanding about the peop… about your understanding to the people around you? That's… that's a Lagna Rashi.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And what you are internally made up of your own inner psyche is basically a Chandra Rashi. And the gap lies between the two, where you're Lagnar Rashi and a Chandra Rashi could be very, very different. And people look at you differently. Like someone could look at me like an extrovert person, but inside, I'm like a shy, docile, passive person. That's very much possible. And this gap kind of makes a person either overperform.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like I'll have to always wear a mask when I get out of in the world because I've chosen a profession like that, that I have to be extroverted, et cetera. So the gap between these two is something that we need to kind of bridge. So that's what we saw yesterday. Today we'll of course take it forward and see more of Nakshatra Dasha and some amount of fast food.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I would request Rohit Rahul to take over before we get into the PPT part of the…
Dr. Karan Mittal: This issue.
GOVINDA Das: Thank you, Doctor Karan.
GOVINDA Das: For presenting this.
GOVINDA Das: So today, what I would like to do…
GOVINDA Das: Is to give certain foundational understanding of.
GOVINDA Das: The psychology of Jyotishastra.
GOVINDA Das: Jyotishastra is like having Brahmastra.
GOVINDA Das: Vendronacharya.
GOVINDA Das: Chose to give Brahmastra to Arjuna.
GOVINDA Das: But he was very reluctant to give it to his son.
GOVINDA Das: Ashwath Thoma.
GOVINDA Das: And certainly not willing to give it to Karana.
GOVINDA Das: It was nothing to do about, oh, Karuna was low cost.
GOVINDA Das: You know, they were not qualified psychological to receive that Astra.
GOVINDA Das: And Ashwatthama comes in.
GOVINDA Das: Challenges his father. How can you not give it to me? I'm your son.
GOVINDA Das: Then, Dronacharya explains, I will not give unless there is a Tapasvi Brahmana.
GOVINDA Das: And a self-controlled Kshatriya.
GOVINDA Das: Karana is not self-controlled and you are not a tapasvi.
GOVINDA Das: But anyway… Dronacharya was forced by Sun.
GOVINDA Das: You know, blackmailed being a son.
GOVINDA Das: And Ronacharya taught him how to use Brahmastra, but not how to withdraw.
GOVINDA Das: And the and the conclusion of that what happened the consequences of that Ashwatthama became destructive.
GOVINDA Das: He released the Brahmastra when there was no need to.
GOVINDA Das: In the modern times, because of the social media, We see… Freshly… not learned.
GOVINDA Das: Freshly informed people have become astrologers.
GOVINDA Das: And because they've freshly learned, And it is like a kick.
GOVINDA Das: What does this CIC do? That CIC, what it does, it basically, it gives you a domain
GOVINDA Das: About somebody else… Which otherwise you did not had.
GOVINDA Das: It's very intoxicating.
GOVINDA Das: And that intoxicating thing, what does it do? It makes one feel overconfident.
GOVINDA Das: To the extent they go precisely saying that chhabbis julaiko accident hoda.
GOVINDA Das: 26th of July, there will be an accident.
GOVINDA Das: Right.
GOVINDA Das: So this kind of confidence or arrogance is not there in the Jyotish Shastra.
GOVINDA Das: Secondly, Right, as Doctor Karan mentioned, explained, if you study.
GOVINDA Das: The Parashar Hora.
GOVINDA Das: Parashar Hora, Parashar Maharshi, the father of Vyasadeva.
GOVINDA Das: When he speaks about Jyotish Shastra, now he's the founder.
GOVINDA Das: The Jyotish Shastra comes from him.
GOVINDA Das: How does he deal with it? He deals Jyothi Shastra as the indicative science.
GOVINDA Das: Not a predictable science.
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
GOVINDA Das: And when we start approaching the Jyotish Shastrage, or you become Jyotish Shastrage, it is like handling the Brahmastra at the wrong space.
GOVINDA Das: I can tell you so many stories.
GOVINDA Das: To the extent where, the Jyoti Shastrage because
GOVINDA Das: You can scare people consciously or unconsciously.
GOVINDA Das: And when people are fearful, they need some support and help.
GOVINDA Das: They're willing to spend anything. People have asked 50 lakh rupees.
GOVINDA Das: People have asked 1 crore rupees. People have asked 10 lakh rupees from those people who have no resources. They are struggling to make money.
GOVINDA Das: And they tell, OK, if you do this, Pooja, if you do this, you pay 10 lakh rupees, then you'll make big
GOVINDA Das: And repeatedly.
GOVINDA Das: Right, getting cheated, not because you're dumb.
GOVINDA Das: We get cheated because we are desperate.
GOVINDA Das: In desperation, person gets cheated.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, it is extremely important to understand
GOVINDA Das: The foundational psychology of Jyothi Shastra.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Jyotish Shastra does not change your disposition.
GOVINDA Das: Jyotish Shastra does not change your destination.
GOVINDA Das: Jyotish Shastra Can be more precise in regards to telling about your past.
GOVINDA Das: And because Jyotish Shastra tells you about your past.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, what happens? Because this is correct, and therefore, whatever is talking about the future will also true. We are trying to control the destination.
GOVINDA Das: When you study Bhagavad Gita, when we study Bhagavad Gita, Ayurveda, Jyotish Shastra, Common Sense, Psychology…
GOVINDA Das: There are 3 principles.
GOVINDA Das: You know, this is…
GOVINDA Das: The purpose of this is not that we will become astrologers. The purpose of this seminar will understand the basic foundational idea how to converse with an astrologer.
GOVINDA Das: You will understand what is my Lagna, what is my Rashi, what is my Nakshatra.
GOVINDA Das: And when you go deeper and deeper about your own nakshatra, your lagna, your rashi, your dasha.
GOVINDA Das: The beauty of Sanatan Dharma is that you become Self-exploring.
GOVINDA Das: Not immediately. You start self-exploring for understanding your psychology, not understanding your destiny.
GOVINDA Das: Do not try to understand your future.
GOVINDA Das: Try to understand your psychology.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, Dr. Karan touched it yesterday.
GOVINDA Das: There are 3 principles.
GOVINDA Das: One is Janma.
GOVINDA Das: One is Karma and one is Goda.
GOVINDA Das: What does Jyotish Shastra do? Jyotish Shastra…
GOVINDA Das: Helps us to understand my Janma.
GOVINDA Das: Now, my Janma is connected to Pratiksha Pramad.
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
GOVINDA Das: It is very easy today to understand.
GOVINDA Das: Because of the DNA, because of the medical facility, that this child is born to this family.
GOVINDA Das: Hmm, okay.
GOVINDA Das: It's a Pratiksha Brahman. It's a Pratiksha Brahman
GOVINDA Das: In particular area to particular family having these kinds of resources, you can have connection to 3, 4, 5 generation to understand what kind of blood is flowing.
GOVINDA Das: One great philosopher, he says, Our birth is not accidental.
GOVINDA Das: Sometime…
GOVINDA Das: Because we want to tell people, oh, birth is not important. Yes, it is not important, but it cannot be neglected completely.
GOVINDA Das: Our birth is not an accident.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, this philosopher says, birth is not an accident.
GOVINDA Das: Our ancestors have paid a price for it.
GOVINDA Das: Mmhm.
GOVINDA Das: So, denying my birth, the significance of my birth, will not help us.
GOVINDA Das: Right, in the modern world.
GOVINDA Das: And for the right reason, it's not that we are not saying, you know, it's for the right reason.
GOVINDA Das: The concept of birth is so much.
GOVINDA Das: undermined, blasted, slandered, neglected because people have used their birthright as everything what they need to control.
GOVINDA Das: Because I'm born Brahmana, because I'm born Kshatriya, because I'm born Vaishya, because I'm born Shudra, the identification with the birth itself becomes my identity.
GOVINDA Das: That is wrong.
GOVINDA Das: Birth is one most important aspect, but when it becomes the only aspect, then it is like Brahmastra destroys our very self.
GOVINDA Das: Very important to understand is Janma. So what did Jyotish Shastra do?
GOVINDA Das: Jyotish Shastra more than Jyotish Shastra, the common sense makes it very clear this is my background.
GOVINDA Das: It is like having a clear audit. It's a white money.
GOVINDA Das: You know how much is there in your bank.
GOVINDA Das: It is the money what you have, you know how much you have, there is no imagination.
GOVINDA Das: The next is Guna.
GOVINDA Das: Alright?
GOVINDA Das: Now, Guna, like Karanji was mentioning yesterday.
GOVINDA Das: In the Jyotish Shastra, there is Lagna.
GOVINDA Das: Lagna is connected to our Ahankar.
GOVINDA Das: What do I identify with?
GOVINDA Das: When I stand in front of my social circle, what do I talk about myself?
GOVINDA Das: And what others talk about myself.
GOVINDA Das: My external, my identity, my ashtitwa.
GOVINDA Das: You cannot deny that astitwa.
GOVINDA Das: That is very important.
GOVINDA Das: That is Ahankar.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: And within that Ahankar, how does Ahankar is formed? Ahankar is formed with a collection of qualities.
GOVINDA Das: Everybody is born with certain qualities, certain disposition.
GOVINDA Das: Some people are very shy.
GOVINDA Das: Some people are bold in their birth only. You must have seen small born babies after one or two years. If they're very outgoing, they don't mind going around.
GOVINDA Das: And some children, literally very shy, they withdraw themselves.
GOVINDA Das: They don't cry.
GOVINDA Das: They don't speak so much.
GOVINDA Das: So what happens as one is growing, we are able to understand one Janma is very protection.
GOVINDA Das: You know, direct.
GOVINDA Das: But Guna is subtle.
GOVINDA Das: Slowly, slowly, slowly, slowly, by observation and by anumana, by hypothetical knowledge, we start understanding darguna.
GOVINDA Das: Nope.
GOVINDA Das: millions of qualities are there. I remember… Somebody mentioned… the Indian movie industry, When it brings the personality.
GOVINDA Das: Ek vekti, ek one person is representing in a movie.
GOVINDA Das: we focus on the political quality of that. A villain is portrayed as a villain.
GOVINDA Das: A hero is portrayed as a hero, but we do not present them as a personality, as a person, because person is a collection of many qualities.
GOVINDA Das: It is not one quality. So therefore, Janma is very clear. Guna is very subtle.
GOVINDA Das: And then comes karma.
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
GOVINDA Das: Please understand, if you understand these three principles in integration, you'll never have over-hyping yourself.
GOVINDA Das: You'll never have a confusion about yourself.
GOVINDA Das: And with these things, when they're connected to your rashi, your lagna, your nakshatra.
GOVINDA Das: You will understand yourself better, and that itself becomes the best solution.
GOVINDA Das: So there is Janma.
GOVINDA Das: Then there is Guna, and then there is Karma.
GOVINDA Das: What is karma? Karma is action.
GOVINDA Das: In the modern world, unfortunately, Because of the professional world has created limitless diversity.
GOVINDA Das: All right.
GOVINDA Das: There is because of limitless diversity.
GOVINDA Das: And one performs karma specifically for.
GOVINDA Das: Increasing their financial resources.
GOVINDA Das: Roti Kapada Makan.
GOVINDA Das: Right? And making it more and more refined.
GOVINDA Das: If I have one bedroom flat, I need a four bedroom flat. If I'm eating ordinary food, I need to eat better food. If I'm traveling to one places, I need to travel to foreign countries. So, roti kapada makaan
GOVINDA Das: That is what connected to karma generally.
GOVINDA Das: We are not talking about specific people.
GOVINDA Das: So, invariably, in the model world, in the modern world.
GOVINDA Das: Guna and Karma are in constant struggle and conflict.
GOVINDA Das: And because they're in constant conflict, what does it do? It does not allow us
GOVINDA Das: To explore ourself properly as I'm exploring myself about my disposition.
GOVINDA Das: But when I go and work, my disposition is completely undermined by my work.
GOVINDA Das: I remember one professor was telling me, He said…
GOVINDA Das: I never wanted to be a professor.
GOVINDA Das: But the college and in engineering college, he was selected as the best professor more than three to four times. Imagine the irony.
GOVINDA Das: He himself is not connecting being a professor.
GOVINDA Das: But he's selected as the best professor.
GOVINDA Das: So his actions are beneficial to the college.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, he's been selected as the best professor.
GOVINDA Das: But his mindset… Right, what he is doing, he is getting the reward.
GOVINDA Das: But the feeling, therefore, Rashi is connected to feeling.
GOVINDA Das: Lagna is connected to identity.
GOVINDA Das: And nakshatra will come later. Nakshatra goes deeper.
GOVINDA Das: Right, so when there is a conflict between my, my Lagna and my Rashi, how I feel.
GOVINDA Das: As against how I do.
GOVINDA Das: Huh? So what does it do? That creates so much of confusion.
GOVINDA Das: And then when you come to the path of spirituality, yesterday I was not able to come because I was doing one.
GOVINDA Das: So there was an urgent talk with some professors.
GOVINDA Das: And there we were discussing this principle only.
GOVINDA Das: the conflict between what I am doing.
GOVINDA Das: And what I feel, and because of that conflict, the growth does not happen. We are perpetually stuck in the first chapter of Bhagavad Gita.
GOVINDA Das: I will not raise my weapons, Krishna.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Arjuna had Krishna to clarify his confusion.
GOVINDA Das: But our confusion itself becomes our life.
GOVINDA Das: And especially when you come to the path.
GOVINDA Das: Oh, sorry.
GOVINDA Das: When you come to the path of spirituality.
GOVINDA Das: Where do we focus? We focus on our constitutional identity.
GOVINDA Das: There are 3 identities.
GOVINDA Das: Right? One is the constitutional identity.
GOVINDA Das: One is the conditional identity, one is the circumstantial identity.
GOVINDA Das: What is constitutional identity? Constitutional identity for one who's practicing spirituality, I am not this body.
GOVINDA Das: I am Atma.
GOVINDA Das: And if you are practicing Vaishnava philosophy, then you feel.
GOVINDA Das: you are told, and you are actually… that is right also, that I am the… Servant of Krishna.
GOVINDA Das: That is connected to your constitutional identity.
GOVINDA Das: Then there is a… Conditional identity, which is called as Swadharma.
GOVINDA Das: And astrology is one of the greatest contribution is to deal with our Swadharma. You don't go to an astrologer to ask him, will I go back to Vaikuntha?
GOVINDA Das: Will I have achieved perfection? Will I go back to God? That is not the domain of an astrologer.
GOVINDA Das: Because going to the spiritual world is not decided by an astrologer, it is given by the Lord himself.
GOVINDA Das: It is given by the Lord, so there is no point in going there.
GOVINDA Das: Right? But what happens? We are so…
GOVINDA Das: So, involved in the constitutional identity.
GOVINDA Das: Our conditional, our swadharma is never dealt with.
GOVINDA Das: When our sadharma is not dealt with.
GOVINDA Das: We try to superimpose our sodharma as our swarupa dharma.
GOVINDA Das: Or our sorupo dharma itself is our sora dharma.
GOVINDA Das: They'll do different thing.
GOVINDA Das: Gopis of Vrindavan did not become sadhus.
GOVINDA Das: They continue to remain gopis. They had no confusion about their swadharma. They were coward girls.
GOVINDA Das: Arjuna was a great devotee of Krishna, but he was very clear about his vadharma, being a warrior.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: Imagine our swadharma is compromised.
GOVINDA Das: Our Swaroop Dharma is understood.
GOVINDA Das: And misunderstand Swaroop Dharma itself is a Swadharma.
GOVINDA Das: And when the Apad Dharma, Apad Dharma is the circumstantial reality.
GOVINDA Das: That circumstantial reality, what does it do? That circumstantial reality or the emergency duty
GOVINDA Das: If that emergency duty itself becomes our identity.
GOVINDA Das: Then also, it gives rise to a lot of pain.
GOVINDA Das: And how do we justify? We justify by saying, oh, this is Kaluga, what can be done?
GOVINDA Das: So, the contribution of Jyotish Shastra, what does it do? With the help of Bhagavad Gita, certainly with Ayurveda.
GOVINDA Das: It has the power to integrate my chanma.
GOVINDA Das: My karma and my guna.
GOVINDA Das: When my Janma Karma Guna are integrated in the Bhagavatam Third Canto.
GOVINDA Das: There is a definition of yoga.
GOVINDA Das: Like Krishna in the Bhagavad Gita, he explained that at all conditions of life, arjuna, tasma yogi, bhava arjuna.
GOVINDA Das: 6.40.
GOVINDA Das: 6 point, not 40, one of the last verses.
GOVINDA Das: Yogi Bhavarjuna, at all condition Arjuna become Yogi, then he says.
GOVINDA Das: You know, yogi namo preservation.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Amongst all the yogis.
GOVINDA Das: One who always remembers Lord Hari within is the best, but the foundation of that one has to be a yogi.
GOVINDA Das: Now, what is the definition of yogi according to the Bhagavatam?
GOVINDA Das: The Bhagavatam explains the definition of yoga.
GOVINDA Das: From one who is practicing yoga, he becomes yogi, and what is that yoga?
GOVINDA Das: Beautiful.
GOVINDA Das: The definition of yoga from the Bhagavatam perspective is, Dharma!
GOVINDA Das: Plus Kriya.
GOVINDA Das: Please understand.
GOVINDA Das: I never saw any other than… other than…
GOVINDA Das: definition given by Krishna like this in the Bhagavatam by Kapil Muni.
GOVINDA Das: I think Maitreya speaks that.
GOVINDA Das: Dharma plus Kriya is equal to yoga.
GOVINDA Das: Now, what is dharma? Dharma is integration of your chanma, your guna, your karma, connected to the laws of life, universal life, that is called as dharma.
GOVINDA Das: Plus kriya, when kriya is connected to dharma, it becomes yoga.
GOVINDA Das: Dharma plus Kriya, if it is not yoga, then it becomes Roga.
GOVINDA Das: Right? In the condition of Roga, what do we do?
GOVINDA Das: We take artificial shelter. One of the disadvantage, like this time during the Purush.
GOVINDA Das: Push it to mass.
GOVINDA Das: Many people went to.
GOVINDA Das: You know, many holy places.
GOVINDA Das: Especially in Brindavan.
GOVINDA Das: And it was crowded like anything.
GOVINDA Das: And… There are many wonderful sadhus who are presenting Hari Katha.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: They are speaking Hari Katha from the perspective Hari Katha.
GOVINDA Das: But unfortunately, many people are renouncing their family.
GOVINDA Das: Even young girls… 20 year old girl, 21 year old girl.
GOVINDA Das: Boys, young boys giving up everything and wanting to go back, go and reside in Brindavan.
GOVINDA Das: I want the Bharaja B Now, this is not recommended by Krishna in the Bhagavad Gita.
GOVINDA Das: Because it cannot become artificially active in the Swarupa Dharma. You achieve your Swarupa Dharma through your Swabhava Dharma.
GOVINDA Das: that cannot be avoided.
GOVINDA Das: So what does Jyotish Shastra do? Jyotish Shastra, once you understand very, it is much deeper than personality study. It is much deeper than the German study of how to understand your personality. It is much deeper than studying the psychological test also.
GOVINDA Das: But unfortunately, most of the time we go and focus on solutions.
GOVINDA Das: predictable future, No. And when you go for the predictable future, you are cheating yourself more first.
GOVINDA Das: Then some unscrupulous Jyotish Shastra will charge you, ask you so much of money, you will be desperate to give, hoping that they will change.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: So what does this study of Jyotishastra help you?
GOVINDA Das: It helps you to understand these three principles in the most profound way.
GOVINDA Das: As you study more deeper and deeper.
GOVINDA Das: You will have proper conversation with Jyotish Shastra, not for seeking.
GOVINDA Das: Fantastic, miraculous solution.
GOVINDA Das: But, you'll have the power to handle
GOVINDA Das: Yourself in such a way and progress nicely and therefore why Kriya is important.
GOVINDA Das: The Jyotish Shastra
GOVINDA Das: While identifying your ego, while identifying your feeling, while identifying your deeper ego, what does it do? It gives more importance to Purushartha.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Purushartha is also defined as karma.
GOVINDA Das: And if that karma is connected to dharma, you become yogi. What kind of yogi? The yogi kind of arjuna where he has.
GOVINDA Das: Bhagawan also.
GOVINDA Das: Andy also has a bhaga.
GOVINDA Das: You know, what is Bhagawan? Bhagawan means, literally means Bhagawan And Bhagavan's resources.
GOVINDA Das: When there are plenty resources, dharma gives rise to sthirta, stability.
GOVINDA Das: And Bhagawan gives rise to joy, happiness, love.
GOVINDA Das: When there is a stirruta and happiness together.
GOVINDA Das: then we are consciously or unconsciously Joining the clan of Arjun.
GOVINDA Das: Yatra Yogeshwara Krishna, Yatra Partha Dan What did Sanjaya tell?
GOVINDA Das: He did not tell only you'll achieve Krishna's love.
GOVINDA Das: Please understand, if you study it carefully, what did he say?
GOVINDA Das: If you follow this teaching.
GOVINDA Das: If you are connected to Krishna and Arjuna, if that combination, what does it give? Dhruva, Neeti, Sri.
GOVINDA Das: Prosperity will be there, determination will be there, stability will be there, and victory will be there.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, without victory, without stability, without prosperity, simply pure spiritual spirit spirituality.
GOVINDA Das: is non-existent. It only exists in our mind.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, Jyotisha and Vastu Shastra, they basically help us to reconcile between my karma.
GOVINDA Das: my Janma and my Guna.
GOVINDA Das: So, what we are doing here for the next 2-3 days.
GOVINDA Das: When you approach any Jyoti Shastra gear, you will know the language.
GOVINDA Das: You will not be fascinated by something what is predicting.
GOVINDA Das: Rather than being fascinated by the prediction.
GOVINDA Das: You'll be honest and humble to accept the reality and rebuild your destiny in such a way. What does it do? It does not simply connect your future.
GOVINDA Das: It connects back to fixing your past.
GOVINDA Das: Once your past is fixed, Then the flow of that Amruta.
GOVINDA Das: The wisdom, the knowledge, the communication.
GOVINDA Das: become very seamless and very profound.
GOVINDA Das: So with this I will ask Karan to speak, and we can take questions later.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Thank you very much.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I'll just share the PPT, and we'll take it forward to Nakshatra and the other.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yesterday, of course, the whole,
Dr. Karan Mittal: focus on yesterday, actually, was the Lagna Rashi and the Chandra Rashi, and the Gunakarama, and Janma, and the Purushartha Prabhuji, elaborated it today, which I touched upon, very briefly yesterday. So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So today, our focus was more on…
GOVINDA Das: Full screen, your chart, is it full screen?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Nick, I don't know, I'
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Is it full screen now?
Dr. Karan Mittal: No?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, okay, thank you, Namanji. Yes, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So the whole focus yesterday was on the Chandra and the Lagnanashi, which we saw how Lagnanashi is basically the world perceives us, what, what the world, like how we kind of display ourselves to the world, it's basically the
Dr. Karan Mittal: masks that we wear, or the impression that we carry, and the Chandra Rashi also being the internal self, or the internal psyche, and that's how the Chandra actually governs our emotions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And that's why Chandra Rashi in Indian astrology, Hindu astrology, holds so much of importance, because it basically tells you
Dr. Karan Mittal: Moving forward, today we'll kind of actually stay with two more questions, which kind of form the pillars of our discussion in this five-day course, is what truly drives me, that is, the indication towards your nakshatra.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And if you kind of look back and see the pattern in your life for the last few months or years, depending upon how aware you are about the pattern, and trying to learn what exactly is the pattern trying to teach you, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So different, time periods in your life have different meanings, or hold different lessons for a person, and that's what is Dasha. So that we'll… we'll stay with these two questions today, and then we'll, of course, go to the Vastu part of the course also, and try to elaborate a bit on Astro Vastu. So these are the two questions
Dr. Karan Mittal: That we kind of focus on. So yesterday we saw how Chandra Rashi is like division into the 12 elements, sorry, into the 12 zodiacs.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And each zodiac kind of also pinpoints to a particular mental psyche that a person holds, that's their internal self. But of course, the human mind is so complex that you cannot divide the whole world into just 12
Dr. Karan Mittal: zodiacs, the cycloids into 12 zodiacs. So, of course, then we moved forward, and we also divided the same zodiacs into 27 nakshatras, or 27 constellations, and that's a nakshatra.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So basically, your Nakshatra, as per the language of astrology, is that particular constellation in which your Chandra is situated. So Chandra Dashi is basically
Dr. Karan Mittal: The Rashi or the Zodiac, where you're…
Dr. Karan Mittal: moon is situated and nakshatra just takes it one step forward we saw that every zodiac is again further divided into constellations we'll come to that diagram later so that nakshatra is basically that particular constellation in which your moon is situated how do we find that how many nakshatras how it is divided we'll come to that so what is basically a nakshatra
Dr. Karan Mittal: Nakshatra is the finer refinement of your psyche, so if the zodiac is like a, like an overview, or your Chandra Rashi is like an overview of
Dr. Karan Mittal: your astrological psyche, Nakshatra goes a few steps deeper and tries to find out more in-depth about how your psyche functions. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So we have one macro picture or a bigger picture of the psyche, and then the further we have the nakshatra, that is your micro picture or that particular aspect that are very prominent in your psyche. It also tells you your signature, like the Mriyagashira nakshatra is a nakshatra of curiosity.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? So it tells you what is your… what is that trait that is kind of your signature trait.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, if you put a Megha Sherah person, either into business, either into scientific arena, or into arts, they approach things with curiosity. They'll always be curious about certain things.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's Nikshira Nakshatra. We'll come to the depths. And if you go to, like, a Nakshatra like Rohini, so Rohini Nakshatra is about creativity. They try to find out things, or they try to do things
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, whether it's an aesthetic work that they're trying to do, you know, performing arts or expressive arts, or if you even put them into some other field, like even a business, you know, corporate life, they'll try to do things more creatively. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Rohini is an extracurricular. So, of course, a Rohini person working in a
Dr. Karan Mittal: the creativity kind of gets enhanced manifold, but you understand that a Rohini person, in any walk of their life, will do things creatively. Even their dressing sense, even the way they talk, even the way they present themselves, will always have a pinch of creativity into it. So Nakshatra tells you what is your signature
Dr. Karan Mittal: trait, what trait actually stands out in you. So, the Chandradashi gives you an overview, and Nakshatra goes a bit deeper. So, I would tell you to just take a moment and, you know, before we get into, again.
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, the further slides, just think, what could be your signature traits? What are your signature traits? What you have seen as a pattern from your childhood until today? And what defines your internal psyche? So, it could be hardworking, it could be creativity, it could be intelligence, curiosity.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know, or maybe on the negative side, doubting everything, pessimism, optimism, whatever it is, just, just take a moment and just try to reflect what's your signature trait.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And maybe you could come up with two or three traits and maybe after the session we have the whole week before the next session, we will also reflect on what trait holds dominance or which is the most prominent one in your life. So that could also be possible. So I'll leave you with that probably question here that you can reflect upon your signature trait. In fact.
Dr. Karan Mittal: During this week, after 2 or 3 days, I'll share a handout in the group, which has the basic
Dr. Karan Mittal: traits and characteristics of the zodiacs and the nakshatras and the legnarashis, so that you can also try aligning or try checking your reflections across these two days from that handout, a very basic one.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's basically your nakshatra. Now, why nakshatra is also of importance will come in probably Vastu, and when we do the Astro Vastu part, is
Dr. Karan Mittal: According to certain very traditional Shastric astrologers, one of the foremost things that a person needs to do when they start, you know, kind of working on their horoscopes, either through Japa, either through Dhana, either through, you know, taking specific efforts to improve certain characteristics, is work on their Nakshatra Lord.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, once you are aware of your Nakshatra Lord, of course, you know what are your characteristics, your signature characteristics, and also from the remedy part, from the
Dr. Karan Mittal: from generating, Japa and Dhana and Tapa, also kind of working on that particular direction in your house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: that particular, presiding deity of that nakshatra, that particular signature trait that you have, starts improvising, you know, certain aspects in your household. So, very traditional astrologers give a lot of importance to the nakshatra. In fact, when we take Sankalpa also in, in,
Dr. Karan Mittal: when we do bigger pujas and yagyas, etc, the nakshatra of the person who's doing the yagya is always chanted. That's how important the nakshatra is. You might avoid… you might not chant the dasha, you might not chant the
Dr. Karan Mittal: But the Chandra Rashi and the Lagna… and the Nakshatra is always kind of taken in the Sankalpa. That's the importance of Nakshatra and Chandra Rashi in the horoscope.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's about the mind's signature nakshatra.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And probably as an activity, I would like you to kind of, you know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, again, you could do it as a homework or do it over the week. I would like to just turn back and see what trait has defined your life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like what trait has been the defining trait of your life? And somewhere you will find the roots of this trait in your nakshatra, like your curiosity. Like for a mikshira person, the curiosity could be the defining trait. He has been curious about different walks of life, has explored different walks of life. For some people, having hope and optimism has been their defining trait. Even in the lowest times, they have kept the optimism and they have, you know, kept walking and that has led success.
Dr. Karan Mittal: them to success. So, kind of looking back at probably the past few years of your life, and seeing what trait has governed the major decisions in your life, will also point
Dr. Karan Mittal: you to what the… what Nakshatra you are, what importance the Nakshatra is, kind of, how much importance or how much governing is the Nakshatra to you right now.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How the zodiac is divided.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, very briefly, we'll just see if, you know, we consider the universe as a 360-degree round, then you'll see that
Dr. Karan Mittal: And this also gives you the answer to the numbers that we saw yesterday. So, one is basically Mesh, Rashi, Aries, and all the other numbers, like, till the number 12, are different different Chandra Rashis. So, if 7 was the number in your first house, in your Lagna, then automatically it points to Libra.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If your moon is sitting in the number 4, probably, okay, in that particular horoscope of yours, then automatically it points to Cancer or Karka as a Chandra Rashi. So it gives you the answer to the numbers of the 12 zodiacs in that horoscope. It gives you the names of the horoscope, but also for this diagram specifically, just have a look at
Dr. Karan Mittal: probably the Aries part, you will see that there are three nakshatras. Two nakshatras are full nakshatras, like Ashwini
Dr. Karan Mittal: And Kritika is like only one part of Kritika, only one number. Like every nakshatra is again divided into four parts. So only one fourth of Kritika comes in Aries. So even a particular zodiac has 2.25 nakshatras into it. So how this changes. So now like I said that Maharaja Sherah is basically a nakshatra of curiosity.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, you will see the Mrikshira Nakshatra comes in Taurus also, Vrishabh also, and Gemini also, that is, in Mithun also
Dr. Karan Mittal: Mithun Rashi is basically a wind element Rashi. So the curiosity of a person of Madhikshira Nakshatra of Mithun Rashi
Dr. Karan Mittal: automatically becomes manifold. It goes to an extent that it can make them restless.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, it kind of… it keeps their mind always overthinking, always, you know, jumping from one… one point to the other. So that's Mikshit of Mithun.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But Taurus, or Vrishav, is a Rashi of the Earth element, or of the Prithvi element. So the curiosity of a Mirikshira Nakshatra in the Vrishav Rashi is grounded curiosity.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So they are curious, but it doesn't disturb them. It doesn't make them restless. It doesn't make them overwhelmed. So the curiosity is more productive and it's used in better ways. So these people come up with more, you know, better ideas or better plans or when they ask questions, they're more grounded questions. They're not just asking questions for the sake of asking. They're more grounded and more questions that are thought over. So it just separates
Dr. Karan Mittal: the, the flavor, like, like yesterday also we saw, the Nakshatra gives flavors to a person's psyche. So similarly, the Malikashira Nakshatra of earth element and the Bayu element, or the wind element in Gemini, changes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And this chart is probably the chart of importance. It's…
Dr. Karan Mittal: we see what Nakshatra we are in, okay? So, like, now, I have been talking about Mikshita, Mikshita, Mikshita, so let's stick to that example. So, Mikshita, Nakshatra, basically, the Lord is Mars, or Mangal of astrology, and the Lord of that, the presiding deity, Som
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the symbol is deer's head. Now, as per the Nakshatra Jyotish, or as per Astro Vastu, or Nakshatra Vastu, we see that if a person really wants to improve his Nakshatra aspects, then working on the direction of Mars in the house, from the Vastu perspective.
Dr. Karan Mittal: From the worship perspective, paying obeisances of just remembering the presiding deity of your nakshatra on a daily basis, monthly basis, weekly basis in form of japa and remembrance. And keeping the symbol of the nakshatra also helps in kind of elevating the effects of the nakshatra. So you don't need to do something very elaborate.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You just need to focus on what.
Dr. Karan Mittal: what are the different traits, or what are the different, governing bodies of that particular nakshatra, and trying to incorporate it in your life in different, different ways. So, so that's about
Dr. Karan Mittal: the nakshatras. So, all the nakshatras, there are… there's one planetary lord, there is one devta lord, and then there are symbols, which kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: signify. These symbols are basically how the Nakshatra looks in the universe. So, these are… these symbols are nothing but how… what actually the Nakshatra depicts, the constellation depicts in the universe, in the solar system. So, that's… that's the symbol. So, in Nakshatra, Jyotish, all three hold
Dr. Karan Mittal: Namanji, if the question can wait, we can take it later. If it's pressing, we can…
Dr. Karan Mittal: I cannot hear you, sorry.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I don't know, it's on my
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, later. Okay, so that's about this. I'll share this chart also in the group for you to kind of look at it later.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And how do you find your nakshatra? So basically, in…
GOVINDA Das: I'm.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes brother, yes brother, sorry.
GOVINDA Das: So can you go back to the previous slide?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, please.
GOVINDA Das: So the very, as Karanji was explaining.
GOVINDA Das: about the… You know, the nakshatras.
GOVINDA Das: Right, as you said, nakshatras are also further divided.
GOVINDA Das: See, in the modern psychology, Like, you must have heard about this, Personality Plus, Enneagram.
GOVINDA Das: Now, there are many such modules which help you to understand your personality.
GOVINDA Das: They're quite fascinating.
GOVINDA Das: But still, they don't go deeper.
GOVINDA Das: It's like identifying which town you are from.
GOVINDA Das: Or they can tell you which area you are from within the town.
GOVINDA Das: But the Jyotish Shastra helps you to go deeper.
GOVINDA Das: More subtler because there are many permutation and combination.
GOVINDA Das: Right. So, therefore, These 27 nakshatras, when they are divided again into 4 parts.
GOVINDA Das: They acquire certain elements connection also.
GOVINDA Das: If you can add that also, you know, the 5 Pancha Mahabhutas.
GOVINDA Das: Earth… Water, fire, air, and ether.
GOVINDA Das: Right, this 5 Mahabhutas.
GOVINDA Das: The Mahabharata explains very fascinatingly the characteristics of the Mahabhutas.
GOVINDA Das: In your personality, in your chart.
GOVINDA Das: The element of earth personality is more based upon your particular charana, the first pada, second pada, third pada, and fourth pada nakshatra.
GOVINDA Das: You develop particular qualities.
GOVINDA Das: The earth element.
GOVINDA Das: The water element.
GOVINDA Das: The fire element.
GOVINDA Das: Sometime a child is born.
GOVINDA Das: I think somebody asked about twins.
GOVINDA Das: Even though twins are born, there is a gap of 1 or 2 minutes.
GOVINDA Das: You know, when the child comes out.
GOVINDA Das: Within that 2 minutes, there is a probability of
GOVINDA Das: some percentage of change in the elements.
GOVINDA Das: They create limitless permutation and combination. And because of that permutation and combination, overall twins have same qualities, but still there is a distinction. That is how the nakshatras go deeper. It is a fascinating thing.
GOVINDA Das: And again, what what the astrology does is if you spend little time.
GOVINDA Das: You start becoming perspective about your own self.
GOVINDA Das: You don't have to be always guided by somebody else.
GOVINDA Das: Others will facilitate, but you start understanding more and more deeper, and when you understand more and more deeper, when there is a self-awareness, self-realization.
GOVINDA Das: that become easier for you know, higher understanding with the universe and Godox.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, alright.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Thank you, Paruji. So, someone asked what's the difference between Lord and the DT, Namanji asked. So, Lord is basically the planetary
Dr. Karan Mittal: presiding Lord, in the sense, out of the nine planets, what planet presides that particular nakshatra? Griha Devata, we call. And DT is basically the Devatas that we talk about in our Shastras. So, like, Ashwini Kumara, Jamaa, Hagini, Brahma, these are the Devatas.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the Lord is basically the Lord out of the nine planets. Of course, the terminologies, we don't have English equivalence. It's, you know, it's Graha and Devata in Sanskrit, the equivalence being Lord and DTO, yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay. Yeah. So how do we find basically a nakshatra? So basically in your horoscope, if you've opened your horoscopes yesterday and saw your Lagna and Chandra Rashis, there are two ways to find out. There's one page which is called as Pashtagraha, in which the degrees of all the planets are given.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So you go to the Chandra, or the moon, and see the next column around the moon, you will get your Nakshatra.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? Or, there is another method, which is called as the Panchanga page of the horoscope. In Panchanga page also, you'll find the five elements, what is your Rashi, which Tithi you were born on, and which Nakshatra you were born in. So, you can also
Dr. Karan Mittal: find out the nakshatra from that particular page, or you can go to the spastagraha, which gives the degrees, etc, of all the planets. Both the places, the nakshatras will be same, because it's basically the location of your
Dr. Karan Mittal: Chandra. So, like, for this person, the Nakshati's Ashlesha, in the 4th division of the Ashlesha, this person was born, because he was born around 2755 degrees, that's
Dr. Karan Mittal: given, in the bracket. So, either the panchanga and, and, or the spashtabra.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So the Rashis tell you how you feel, what's your psyche, but the Nakshatra tells you what are your signature characteristics, what drives you, and what drains you. So there could be a negative part also. Like I said, in the Mrikshira, the same curiosity that is productive for the person of Mrikshira and Bhrishabh Rashi becomes overwhelming and exhausting for a person of Mithun Rashi Mrikshira.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, you have to then channelize ways to reduce the… because, as I said, Mithun Rashi, as Prabhuji also said, is the wind element Rashi. So, wind kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: Again, makes you restless, and combined with the restlessness of the mind, that is curiosity, it kind of escalates the whole thing. So you have to find ways to kind of, either through mindfulness practices, et cetera, reduce this part, and also through different other practices, control the pranavayu and apanavayu to reduce the restlessness.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And then… and then probably the next part is.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Dasha system. Dasha system is basically what kind of… so, till now, we have seen what are your traits, what is the ground reality, or what kind of governs you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But where does the element of time come into? What will happen, when will it happen, et cetera, comes in through the Dasha system. And the Dasha system is what tells you what time is good for probably education, what time is good for marriage, what time gives you more probability for having a success in business. So that's the Dasha system. So we have the nine planets.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And every planet is given a particular number of years.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, with the total becomes 120 years, it's called the Vinshottari Dasha system.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? And every planet has different, different numbers. Like, Ketu will have a different number, Shani has 19, Buddha has… So, different planets have a different…
Dr. Karan Mittal: number of years, and that is the particular point of time when these planets exert more influence in your life. So, if you're going through a Jupiter Dasha, or a Guru Mahade Shah, then definitely that period is the period of learning.
Dr. Karan Mittal: that period is a period of spirituality, that is a period of kind of achieving whatever you want to achieve, even in the financial and professional aspect of your life, because Guru is a planet that is basically supporting you in your endeavors. Of course, there are micro-detailings to it, but that's the period. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, doing… taking these decisions in that period of your Guru Mahadev Shah will automatically increase the intensity or the power of that particular decision, because Guru is supporting you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Similarly, the Saturn, we kind of criticize Saturn, but Saturn, of course, is a planet of learning.
Dr. Karan Mittal: learning through hard work, through hardships, through difficulties in life. So, that is a period when a person needs to probably cool down, or kind of relax a bit, or kind of work on his more dharmic aspect of his life, and try to increase the dharmic ocean, so that the learnings come in soon, more of contemplations.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Etc so so kind of aligning the decisions of your life as per your dasha and you see the period is 120 years so it's not possible that a person like in current age sees all the dashas they see 7 6 5 depending on when it starts so these are the number of dashas that a person might be able to see in this life so accordingly aligning your decisions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: From the Dasha perspective, and every Dasha
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like, now you'll see that it's not possible that Venus is 20 years, and
Dr. Karan Mittal: throughout the 20 years, the flavor of the learnings or the patterns in the life remain the same? No. So, our rishis are again a bit more micro. Every particular dasha is again divided into 9 planetary periods. So, 20 is again further divided into smaller
Dr. Karan Mittal: or milder or minor dashas of, again, the same cycle being repeated. So you will have a bigger flavor of, you know, base note of Venus, but the finer notes or top notes could be Saturn, Jupiter, Moon.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Keturahu, etc, etc, etc. So that's how The Dasha system works.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And I usually give the analogy of the seasons, it's like a season. If you're trying to kind of reap the benefits of spring season in the winter season, it's not possible.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You cannot, you know, do things, or if you're trying to, you know, sow a seed that requires lots of water in summer season, it will really not work, because rains are far away. So, the Shah system, the best analogy is to look at, like, seasons and try to align
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like in Ayurveda or in INR, life also be aligned in our activities as per the season.
Dr. Karan Mittal: This is more like a universal method of seasons, which is aligning a life as per seasons.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, you see on the right side, this is like a dasha system, okay? You see, like, it starts with bud, that is mercury, and then it lasts for a particular number of years, okay? These are
Dr. Karan Mittal: the minor dashas, these are not the mahadashas, so the number of years have changed over here, but you'll see that Buddha's for 3 years, Ketu is, like, for again, like, around 7-8 years. So, so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, it's like… it's like… it starts at a particular date, ends at a particular date, and the cycle keeps on running.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The microcycle, the major cycle, it just keeps on running, running, running, running. So this is how the Dasha system works, and you start… you see, it starts with Buddh, then ends at Shani. So once Shani gets over, then again the cycle will run. Okay? So this keeps on going.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay, so this is basically, analysis… yes, Virjit?
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, thank you.
GOVINDA Das: Another interesting part of Jyotish Shastra, as
GOVINDA Das: Dr. Karan is speaking the Nakshatra.
GOVINDA Das: Lagner, Ashen, Naud, Dasha The Dasha principle, sometime when people are going through Rahu Dasha.
GOVINDA Das: You know, when they go through Raudasha.
GOVINDA Das: You'll be scared. Oh, my God! Now your raudha is going through.
GOVINDA Das: Or sometimes people celebrate, oh, my Jupiter is going on.
GOVINDA Das: Alright.
GOVINDA Das: But what Jyotish Shastra and Bhagavad Gita in particular teaches.
GOVINDA Das: That no dasha is specifically positive or negative.
GOVINDA Das: No planets… Yes, the planet themselves, when you study, that sun… Jupiter, Chandra.
GOVINDA Das: You know, they are considered as very good planets.
GOVINDA Das: Rahu, Shani, Mars are not considered as good planet.
GOVINDA Das: the good and… Bad.
GOVINDA Das: in your chart, Has a different impact.
GOVINDA Das: Sometime Rahu can be beneficial.
GOVINDA Das: And sometime the Jupiter can give rise to certain issues also, health issues also.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, in the Parashar Hora, when Parashar Maharshi presents.
GOVINDA Das: You know, he's very blunt in regards to speaking the negative side of the chart also.
GOVINDA Das: No, he has no filters.
GOVINDA Das: Because it's presenting the knowledge, he's not presenting it to some particular person.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: So… the over… Over glorification of one's dasha.
GOVINDA Das: Or scaring about one's dasha is not again very mature presentation by a Jyotish Shastragia.
GOVINDA Das: It's a land of duality. Yesterday I was talking to our school children.
GOVINDA Das: I know, giving an example of The greatest footballer.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, there is a debate whether is goat or not.
GOVINDA Das: Cristiano Ronaldo, right?
GOVINDA Das: Now, what is his background?
GOVINDA Das: He's the one who has lost Maximum number of phenolic kicks.
GOVINDA Das: Sab siyaba.
GOVINDA Das: But he also is the one who has got the highest number of penalty kick.
GOVINDA Das: So what does it indicate? It indicates 50 50%.
GOVINDA Das: So the land of duality, what does it do? Overall, one's life.
GOVINDA Das: Is not designed as a perfect chart because we are not Devatas.
GOVINDA Das: Or not completely imperfect chart.
GOVINDA Das: Because we are completely broken beings.
GOVINDA Das: It's in between, therefore there are many permutation and combination.
GOVINDA Das: Your dasha may not be good, but your lagna may be very good.
GOVINDA Das: or your lagna must be, you know, not so good, but your dasha period is good. At least for 10-12 years, you'll have great time, so enjoy that particular time properly, and collect more resources to deal with your challenging situations.
GOVINDA Das: Right? So, therefore, please understand, no chart
GOVINDA Das: or know the systems of Jyotish Shastra.
GOVINDA Das: Will give only positive or only negative result. It is a combination of good planets, bad planets.
GOVINDA Das: The main dasha, then there is antaradasha, then again there is subdashas, there is pratyantra dasha, there is sukshma dasha, there are 4 divisions of dasha also. Therefore, jyotishastra is a fascinating psychology.
GOVINDA Das: Focus on the psychology, do not focus on the prediction.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, okay.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, correct.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. So, yes, so… so every… everything has, of course, the micro aspects to it. So every dasha also, depending on where the planet is placed, etc, the effects might reduce and increase,
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yes. So, so basically, this is what we saw as the Lagna being
Dr. Karan Mittal: the figure that the world sees you as, the Rashi being your inner thoughts and feelings, Nakshatra being your unique style, motivation, what drives you, your signature, and the Dasha being the chapter or the pattern that is playing in your life right now. So, when we try to understand astrology, when we now get into the Vastu part of it, we try to understand why
Dr. Karan Mittal: why Nakshatra and Dashar are so important from an astrological or Nakshatra Vastu perspective is that if you're aligning the directions
Dr. Karan Mittal: of your particular workplace or your house, depending on your nakshatra and your current dasha, automatically, it starts becoming a bit more favorable from a Vastu perspective. Now, you might say that
Dr. Karan Mittal: How is it possible that everyone will have a different nakshatra lord, different dasha going?
Dr. Karan Mittal: at a particular point of time in their life, in a particular… in a specific house, then how can we keep on aligning 8 directions? Of course, aligning all 8 directions is what is…
Dr. Karan Mittal: expected but supposedly if you're not able to align all the directions for everyone then the room that you work in work at or the room that you live in kind of aligning the plan the directions of these planets depending on your Nakshatra and Dasha starts improvising things as per the Vastu perspective we'll come to it in detail but why Nakshatra and Dashas are so important
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, of course, we saw that… we saw this yesterday in the Siddhanta of Yatpinder Tagrande, but also the below verse is from Chirag Samhita, and it also says the same thing, that, you know, the entities and beings that exist in the universe, same exist in the human beings. So, if you talk about
Dr. Karan Mittal: The planets, they also exist, if you talk about the demigods also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: if you go as per pure, Shastric Memonsa principles, every demigod is, like, sun is there in the eyes, and then, of course, the hands are governed by Indra, the legs are governed by Vishnu. So these are the principles that the whole… all the demigods are placed at different
Dr. Karan Mittal: parts of your body. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: there is a correlation between what exists in the universe, whether it's the five elements, the nine planets, the demigods, and their existence in our body. So that's the principle on which Vastu is also based.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Coming back to Vastu proper now. If you see, like this is a basic compass, we're just trying to understand the directions before we get into how to map our houses, is there are 4 cardinal directions which we all know of, north, east, south, west.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And they both exist in, you know, pairs, so north pairs with south, east pairs with west, so that we know of.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But in Vastu, we go a bit further. In the basic Vastu, we go a bit further. The direction that is exactly between north and east becomes the northeast, that is the Ishanyakun.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The direction between east and south becomes the southeast, the Agnaya.
Dr. Karan Mittal: The south and the west.
Dr. Karan Mittal: is southwest becomes the native or negative.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the west and the north, the direction that is in the center is basically Vyavya or the northwest zone. So what you do is you put a compass wherever you need to take a direction. You'll get these four directions as two intersecting lines. And you just go 45 degrees or the midpoint between east and the north direction.
Dr. Karan Mittal: is basically the direction that is between. North and East becomes Ishanya, East and South becomes Agnir, etc. So how we take it, we'll come to it, but basically.
Dr. Karan Mittal: How do we do that? How do we take… The directions is…
Dr. Karan Mittal: you… you take the layout of your house, and go to the perimeter, or the edges of the house, and try to create a nearest, like, tangle, or a square, whatever is possible, okay? So… so…
Dr. Karan Mittal: You kind of, you know, kind of join all the edges of the perimeter of the house, and from one corner, you kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Extend the line to the other corner, like you join points A and C and B and D of that, that particular rectangle or the square, and you find the center of your house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, this holds a lot of importance in Vastu. This center point of the house is called as the Brahmastan of your house, or the center of your house. It's basically the center that kind of charges. It's like the navel point. It charges the whole house, so that's the Brahmastan of the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You take the directions of the house from this point. So what do we do is, what I do is, I go to this point, I keep a compass over here, and once I keep a compass over here, I'll come to know that, okay, this is the north.
Dr. Karan Mittal: this is probably the west, this is east, this is south, and automatically then point B becomes, you know, northeast, C becomes southeast, D becomes… in a square house. In a square house, it's very easy.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But similarly, if you go to the rectangular house, if you see over here, again, we are making a rectangle, okay? We are, again, kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: intersecting, like, the joining points A and C and B and D, and trying to find the Brahmastan again over here.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And again, in the Brahmastan, I go and stand, and I try to find out the directions. So you cannot find out directions, and like, from any other point, it's necessary that you go to the Brahmastan of the house to find the accurate directions, okay? If you change the directions, if you change the place from where you're standing, the directions will change.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So that's how it is. Now, we don't have houses in Mumbai or…
Dr. Karan Mittal: Like, which are completely square or rectangular. So that's how this is. So suppose this is probably a house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And this part is missing from the house. We don't have this part because it's, like, that's how the flat is constructed. Still, what I'll do is I'll try to create the nearest rectangle. So this is the nearest rectangle that I created. I'm considering that this
Dr. Karan Mittal: is a part of the house, I'm making this rectangle, and I'm trying to find the brahmastan
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? If you have any… while you do this exercise over the week, if you have any queries, you can please put it on the group with the layout. We'll try to assist you to find the exact Brahmastan of your house. So this is where the Brahmastan is. Again, I'll stand here, and I'll try to take the directions. Okay? So this is how the directions look like.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Brahmastan, Brahmastan, this purple thing is the Brahmastan, I'm standing over here, and see, the north is directly in front of me, okay? Now, this whole zone.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's between these two lines, becomes the north zone.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: this part becomes the northeast zone. So you're seeing it's like a triangular structure of 45 degree angle. This angle is 45 degree. So these structures become
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, 45 degree each, and I divide the house into 8 different directions in the preliminary master. So, that's about taking the directions. You, like, need to make this grid or layout.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? And then you need to be vigilant, or you need to start finding out that what element of my house, or what activity of my house lies in which direction. So in this house, for example, in northeast, I have a bedroom.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In east, I have a toilet. In southeast, again, I have a bedroom. In south, I have a toilet, okay, and a washbasin. In southwest, again, I have kitchen. West, I have
Dr. Karan Mittal: half of the other part of the kitchen, and in northwest, I have the living room, and then probably a balcony. So you just need to start finding out what element, or what… what, activity is happening in that part of the house. That's the basic work that we need to do.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Before we move forward, let's try to understand the planets and the different directions that each of the directions are ruled by — different planets that rule each of these directions. So we start with the east. In Indian astral — in Indian Mastu, we always start with the east. So we keep the east at the top, and then we move.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Okay? In Feng Shui and other Western adaptations of Vastu, we keep the north at the top, and because it becomes a bit easier, based on the compass, because compass always spawns at the north. But in Indian Vastu, we start with the Purva. So, the planet of the eastern direction is sun.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Now, visualize what sun actually means to you. So, sun is power, sun is fame, sun is vitality, sun is health. So, all these directions are kind of governed by the… all these qualities are kind of governed by the sun, and these become the qualities of your each direction.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Similarly, the Southeast, as the name suggests, we saw the name was Agnea. Agnea means Agni. So, basically, the element… we'll get into the details of it in the third session, but… but Agnea is basically Agni. So, the element of
Dr. Karan Mittal: The southeast is fire, and now you need to understand what does the fire mean, so it becomes activities, it becomes, it's just, so it's activity, sensuality, it's, it's, also it's governed by Venus, the planet of creativity and sensuality, so both these aspects get combined into the Akhnaya cone, so one is fire element.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so the activity of fire, or the aggression of the fire. Also, the Venus, so sensuality comes in, relationship comes in, okay? Fire also governs your digestive system, so we call it jataragni. So, the digestive health also comes through the agni account.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Then we go to the south, and the south is the direction of Mars. So… so… so the qualities of Mars, that is strength, discipline, and boundaries, okay, basically are governed by… by the south direction. Now, I was speaking about Nakshatra Vastu, so the Lord of the Bhrigashira Nakshatra is basically Mars.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, a person who's of Nikshira Nakshatra will basically try to align the south direction of his bedroom or his workplace, try to clear off in the, you know, all the waste things that are kept in the south direction, clean it up, keep it well-lit, kind of put
Dr. Karan Mittal: some things that enhance the southern direction, will automatically energize the nakshatra of that particular person, because we are doing the remedy, or we are working on the,
Dr. Karan Mittal: on the nakshatra through the space wave, from a way where we are aligning our spaces to suit us.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Southwest is basically Rahu and it also signifies Earth element and Earth element is basically the element of grounding and stability so houses where Southwest is is not proper Etc will have issues with grounding and stability they will have more influence of Rahu and Rahu creates illusion disturbance of the mind Etc so these these aspects will be seen so that's another Rahu like Rahu's influence on the
Dr. Karan Mittal: this direction. It's also earth element, so the grounding and stability. Now, suppose
Dr. Karan Mittal: The Rahu in my horoscope is weak.
Dr. Karan Mittal: and also the house, Nairukta, the southwest zone of the house is not proper, it's either cart, or it has something, negative over there, then how do I increase the earth element in my life? Because
Dr. Karan Mittal: because if Nehru Te is cut, Dhrau's influence will kind of make my mind more and more, agitated, more, you know, deceptive, it will create illusions, misunderstandings, etc. So I need to increase the earth element in my life, and I will increase it by increasing it in my deeds, so probably I'll
Dr. Karan Mittal: choose the chair which has, you know, a bigger backrest, so it kind of gives me that support and the grounding. Probably I try to walk bare feet so that I get… I am more in connection with the earth, so that increases the earth element. I will try to
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, eat things that are a bit more raw, so that that earth element increases in my body and my mind. So it will automatically bring in that grounding and that stability, and reduce the mind's overthinking or elusive patterns. West is against Saturn.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So Saturn is basically Shani, and it's basically meant for patience, maturity, completion. It is also meant for, the people who serve you. So these are the aspects governed by the western direction. Northwest is Moon.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's also air element, so basically movement, flexibility, mental health, mental well-being is also governed by Northwest. North is Mercury.
Dr. Karan Mittal: basically, again, intellect, opportunities, flow, because North is considered to be the most auspicious direction, and from, from the aspect of prosperity, East is considered from the aspect of health, and Northeast is considered from the aspect of spirituality. We'll come to the details in the next session.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And northeast is finally water element governed by Jupiter. So now how this works. Suppose my Jupiter Dasha is going, going on, and, and the northeast of my house is always cluttered, is always, you know, having all the, all the negative things that
Dr. Karan Mittal: can be kept, like it's a storehouse, or storeroom of the house, then automatically, the power that the Jupiter Dasha should have in my horoscope, or the benefits that the Jupiter Dasha should give, my chart is aligned.
Dr. Karan Mittal: my efforts are aligned, so the universe is aligned, my body is aligned, I'm trying to make those efforts, but because the Northeast is corrupted, or Northeast is not
Dr. Karan Mittal: is not kept well, then automatically the effects of that dasha will not come to its maximum potency, or at that optimum level. So, trying to align the directions of your house as per your nakshatra and your dasha automatically starts aligning the benefits of your household.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So this is about the 8 directions, and also, maybe as a homework, once you map your 8 directions, you come to this
Dr. Karan Mittal: chart very approximately, then start writing down that the north direction has probably, you know, the… or maybe the northeast has the bedroom now, or the east has the toilet now. Logically, east is meant for health, or is meant
Dr. Karan Mittal: As the sun's direction, and you're putting the toilet over there, then automatically you're putting something that… that holds a negative energy,
Dr. Karan Mittal: symbolism in the east direction, or in the northeast direction, or in the south direction. So, try putting in what element is where. So, also now, now, northeast is probably water element, it's called the Ishanya cone. Now, water element, if you have your kitchen.
Dr. Karan Mittal: a kitchen as fire element, so putting an anti-element over there in that direction. So just trying to make the note of this, and then we work with the,
Dr. Karan Mittal: With the layout of your house as days pass.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And before… before… We end for today's, session.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So your house is basically a symbol of your horoscope also?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of your body also, and once you know your house properly, or your chart properly, you'll be able to start finding these correlations that exist between your
Dr. Karan Mittal: learnings that what's happening in your life currently, the astrological symbolism, and also the Vastu, or the house, or your house. So going… coming from a very physical body perspective.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the house is kind of, you know, kind of… it's in Shastra that said that the Vastu Purusha kind of lays on his abdomen in every house. So what you're seeing in the diagram over here is basically a symbol of Vastu Purusha.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And now you see that the northeast has the head of the Vastu Purusha, the southwest has the feet of the Vastu Purusha, and the abdomen is there somewhere in the Brahmast
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, there are, as per Shastri Vastu principles, if there are issues in different body parts of the Vastu Purusha, those same issues start reflecting in the inhabitants of the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, yakpindeta brahmana just doesn't hold to the planetary part, it holds to the body parts, it holds to the chakras, it holds to the devatas. So, everything that happens in the shastras, from the Samkhya perspective, has a symbolism in our body, in our house also.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, I think with that, we can probably conclude today's
Dr. Karan Mittal: thing, and then we'll take it up next time, Project. Yes.
GOVINDA Das: Any questions or comments.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah.
Abhijit Agarwal: I guess so.
Abhijit Agarwal: Tony, may I?
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, yeah.
GOVINDA Das: Yes.
Abhijit Agarwal: Pretty,
Abhijit Agarwal: The thing is that, we had a very good discussion today, like, there are many things which have been, you know, personally, I have never knew.
Abhijit Agarwal: To go ahead, I was requesting, it's a humble request, if we can get today's recording, so that we can, when I come next day, the next class, I can be well prepared what has happened today. So, in order to, you know, continue from where we have to end, and where we are going to start ahead.
GOVINDA Das: Okay, we will, we'll ask them, we'll ask the coordinators to post it on the… Recording. Correct. Thank you.
Abhijit Agarwal: Thank you.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, no one.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You're not audible, Nama.
Alpa Sampat: Hello, Prabhuji, Hare.
GOVINDA Das: Yes.
Alpa Sampat: Bye!
Alpa Sampat: Actually, I joined late today, I could not register yesterday, so could you please provide the recordings of yesterday and today's Prabhuji?
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, yeah, we will immediately tell them to post it.
Alpa Sampat: Yeah, due to some reason, I could not register yesterday.
GOVINDA Das: Nice, nice.
Alpa Sampat: Yeah, yeah. Hare Krishna Prabhuji. Thank you.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Namanji, you'll have to edit type. You're not aud All right.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yeah, maybe we could type if it's possible, and then we can take someone else's question.
Dr. Karan Mittal: You know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Vipulgi?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Can you answer your question?
vipul sutrave: Hare Krishna Prabhuji, thank you so much. This is Whipple's wife, Tulsi Lata Devidasi, and my husband's name is Rajendra Kumandas.
vipul sutrave: I'm so happy to… we are very happy to be in this, thing. So, my question is, Prabhuji, can we use astrology in management?
vipul sutrave: Especially Skawn Temples Management.
vipul sutrave: So, the thing is that I am learning astrology for the past 3 years.
vipul sutrave: I've been giving some astrological, what do you say, insights.
vipul sutrave: for Brahmacharya Ashram, for temple management.
vipul sutrave: And, you know, to have a hand… hand-on-hand with the public concerns.
vipul sutrave: So, the main point I raised is, according to astrology, 36 to 42 years, Saturn is mature, and after that, only a person can ascertain that I will be in Brahmacharya.
vipul sutrave: But, scone management gives pulmatjari saffron to 25-year-old boy.
vipul sutrave: Who is not even sure that he will be in the ashram or not. Like, my own brother, he was in Ramachari Ashram for 11 years.
vipul sutrave: And I… we always follow astrology, and his chart was showing that he has very good stars for getting married, Gulhastha.
vipul sutrave: But he, he, he discarded it like anything. He said, astrology is not a, great devotional services above astrology and all.
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
vipul sutrave: But finally, she fell in love and we got married.
vipul sutrave: And I said that, see, this is what it is, when you are not pure devotee. And then you are telling that, again, you know.
vipul sutrave: brushing aside astrology, it's not good. So my question is that, why can't we take the basic concept that after 36 to 42, midlife crisis comes?
vipul sutrave: Broad term, it is called midlife crisis. Otherwise, in astrology, it is called, shani maturity life, which is…
vipul sutrave: So, Shani matures at 42 years, after 42 years. Why can't a scorn management
vipul sutrave: Had this basic thing of understanding that human milestone, just like the child walks in 1 year, talks in 3 years, 5th year he can go to studies, 8th year he has some milestone, 13th year he had a puberty.
vipul sutrave: And 18 years, he has a teenage. So, in the 36 to 42 years, he is fully grown individual.
vipul sutrave: That is a milestone of human.
vipul sutrave: So…
GOVINDA Das: Hare Krishna Mataji, you are giving a… Yes.
vipul sutrave: Oh, that's my question.
GOVINDA Das: Yes, yes.
vipul sutrave: Why not astrology be practically applied in ISKCON management?
GOVINDA Das: So the point is, what you're saying is reality. What you said is Shastra, even Sanatana Goswami.
GOVINDA Das: Tomorrow we will discuss what Sugadeva Goswami the 5th Kant of the Bhagavatam, how the planet influence.
vipul sutrave: Mmm.
GOVINDA Das: But again, you have to see the historical reality of every organization.
GOVINDA Das: There is, as I was mentioning about the circumstantial duty.
GOVINDA Das: There are… in emergency, something was done, that emergency has become a protocol now, so that has to be dealt, so… it's it's much… you're discussing from a very deeper…
GOVINDA Das: concept of establishing proper system within the GV system. What you are speaking is absolutely connected to Shastra, but how to bring it into the
GOVINDA Das: The system… Is the question because there are people who misquote.
GOVINDA Das: About the… about the scriptures.
GOVINDA Das: that if you surrender to Krishna, you can overcome all your karma. If you have a guru, you'll overcome. You know, these are all, these are all, like, I… I heard somebody say, even in the political rally.
GOVINDA Das: There is a political pitch, and there is a governance pitch.
GOVINDA Das: Even the Hindu political party, when they are doing a…
GOVINDA Das: When they are doing election rally.
GOVINDA Das: It is based upon Hindu identity, but the governance is extremely socialist.
GOVINDA Das: You know, there is a contradiction between what they speak and what they govern.
GOVINDA Das: Now, are they hypocrites?
GOVINDA Das: No, the entire system is so much complicated, it takes…
GOVINDA Das: Shani means what? Shani means it's a slow process.
GOVINDA Das: Shani does not create a revolution, suddenly.
GOVINDA Das: So now you got something you have experienced in your own family, so you're studying also astrology, you know, so slowly, slowly.
GOVINDA Das: Sometime it happens from the ground level, and when the authorities, higher level, they understand, they pick up.
GOVINDA Das: Because… Most Prabhupada disciples, when they came.
GOVINDA Das: They did not have any connection to Jyotish Shastra being the coming from that background. Whatever they understood sincerely, they practice. But there are people who are slowly, slowly doing it. So with patience, consistency, then the corollary scriptures, Jyotish Shastra is light.
GOVINDA Das: It will be used. There are people who are using. I know about it. It will happen.
GOVINDA Das: But, yes, what you explained is correct.
GOVINDA Das: And slowly it is happening, that's what I.
vipul sutrave: Continuing this, one more thing, that they say that Bhakti Siddhanta Saraswati Maharaj.
GOVINDA Das: No, what we will do, Matajay, I can talk to you separately. This.
vipul sutrave: Okay, no problem.
GOVINDA Das: Because…
vipul sutrave: Okay, can I, can I get your time, Sophie? When can I get.
GOVINDA Das: I'll talk to you separately, okay?
vipul sutrave: When probably.
GOVINDA Das: We can talk tomorrow only.
vipul sutrave: Okay.
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
GOVINDA Das: Yes.
GOVINDA Das: So we'll take one or two questions. We can talk 100%.
GOVINDA Das: You are mentioning our predictable future as you are mentioning that you should not be the only goal.
GOVINDA Das: So my question is, to what extent should try to know and time the thing so that the future is as peaceful, predictable as possible?
GOVINDA Das: Interestingly, one very learned scholar was talking to me recently.
GOVINDA Das: He's also very deeply involved in understanding physics.
GOVINDA Das: You know, so he was telling me how physics work.
GOVINDA Das: No, the matter when we see the matter.
GOVINDA Das: You know, the constant, there is parinam, there is, there is, there is a moment and there is a consequences.
GOVINDA Das: Generally, on a superficial level, We focus on the consequences, we are trying to fix our future.
GOVINDA Das: But now there are certain particle which the scientific community, when they went deeper, they realize rather than fixing the future, it fixes the past.
GOVINDA Das: Hmm?
GOVINDA Das: Very deep.
GOVINDA Das: Similarly, Jyotish Shastra It's not about dealing with the future, that is karma, that is karmakanda.
GOVINDA Das: we are basically uncovering the past, the full of knowledge, full of bliss, and full of eternality. When you fix your past, your present and future is naturally
GOVINDA Das: becomes very… You know, within your control, but if you try to fix your future, which is
GOVINDA Das: Which is basically magical, fascinating, you know, titillating.
GOVINDA Das: And it's very important to understand this. When you fix your past, your present and future also fixed. Therefore, predictability, as Dasha Karanji was mentioning, we can talk about that. What could be the probable situation you might face?
GOVINDA Das: Rather than you will face. So there is a distinction between what might and what you will.
GOVINDA Das: Because when you have a predictable future, you lose the concept of
GOVINDA Das: Dealing with uncertainty, so your Sharanagati is disturbed and your Purushartha is disturbed.
GOVINDA Das: The human endeavor is disturbed and your Saranagati is also disturbed, so then element of even in the Mahabharata, Vyasadeva represents that concept of, you know, daiva.
GOVINDA Das: He gives an… he comes and gives certain indication to the Pandavas.
GOVINDA Das: But does not stamp their future. This is what is going to happen. So that is his personality. So it is always better to focus on fixing the past.
GOVINDA Das: so that my present and future is handled by the practicing personality, whether it is Karma Yoga or when it is Bhakti Yoga.
GOVINDA Das: No?
GOVINDA Das: Anything you want to add, Karan, about this?
GOVINDA Das: You can take one more question up, Shubham.
GOVINDA Das: And then we'll stop, and we can take next time. If a particular time is good, and something does it mean that we are naturally motivated, or circumstances create in such a way that we take up that, regardless of whether we consult astrology or not.
GOVINDA Das: The interesting part is, When you have an indication of your timing, your dasha.
GOVINDA Das: An offensive army is better suited than the defensive army.
GOVINDA Das: Hmm?
GOVINDA Das: Very simple logic.
GOVINDA Das: So when you don't have an indication about your psychological personality, you simply go through that.
GOVINDA Das: I remember… You know, talking to some people, they have an indication of addiction.
GOVINDA Das: Those who get to know that there are certain indication of addiction, then you can take greater precautions.
GOVINDA Das: Either to keep it totally dormant or minimize it.
GOVINDA Das: But if you do not, then what happens? Your ignorance becomes responsible for experiencing whatever is supposed to happen. So, Jyotish Shastra, one very interesting part is.
GOVINDA Das: Jyotish Shastra is not to make it happen, especially those negative activities.
GOVINDA Das: No? And therefore, in the Bhagavad Gita, Krishna explains very profound words. Mataji, you can also… 5.15. If Krishna himself makes it very clear in the Bhagavad Gita.
GOVINDA Das: In his name, we talk about Sharanagati. What does he say? Nadate kasachit papam nadate sukrutim vibhu.
GOVINDA Das: He says, my dear Arjuna, I do not take anybody's good karma or bad karma.
GOVINDA Das: Why living and it is suffering? Living and it is suffering not because of their karma.
GOVINDA Das: You know, karma is simply understanding and acting. Krishna says they suffer because of their jnana is covered by ignorance.
GOVINDA Das: So therefore, it is very important to understand when that awareness is there, consciousness is there.
GOVINDA Das: The impact of negative can be reduced.
GOVINDA Das: And when the impact of negative is reduced, when your positive time is coming, you have no loan.
GOVINDA Das: Right? When you start making money, but if you have a big loan, so even after making money, it takes more time to undo your loan. So astrology is also like that. Bad timing is like a loan.
GOVINDA Das: good timing is like a profit, but in your bad time out of ignorance, if you build huge loan, even if the good time comes, it takes longer time. So therefore, awareness, knowledge, has the power to minimize
GOVINDA Das: power to handle it or power to keep it dormant so that it doesn't grow.
GOVINDA Das: So therefore, timing is very important.
GOVINDA Das: So I'll stop here and meet again tomorrow at the same time, 7 o'clock.
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Next slide, Debraji. Next.
GOVINDA Das: And my number is there in the back.
Dr. Karan Mittal: 30 seconds.
GOVINDA Das: You can connect with me. You can see in that group.
GOVINDA Das: Okay.
Abhijit Agarwal: Thank you, Burji.